Hello today's דף daf is ק"ב kuf-beis 102 and we pick up
at עמוד amud ק"ב kuf-beis עמוד ב׳ amud beis and we are
actually switching gears, not really switching gears, you know, because it's all
this huge אגדתא Aggadata and somehow the pieces all talk to one
another. So just to remind you though, you know, the opening section
was about עולם הבא Olam Ha-ba and somebody who doesn't believe in
תחיית המתים Techiyas Ha-meisim doesn't have עולם הבא, Olam Ha-ba, so it
was about תחיית המתים Techiyas Ha-meisim and עולם הבא Olam Ha-ba and
ימות המשיח. Yemos Ha-mashiach. Then we got to the some little part
there about like you know somebody who's הוגה שם באותיותיו. hogeh shem
b'osyosav. And anyway we got to אפיקורוס, Apikoros, which is not the
רמב"ם Rambam's idea, which is like somebody who a heretic who doesn't
believe in certain you know dogmas. For the גמרא Gemara it's somebody
who disrespects rabbinic authority and then that led to like a whole
series of אגדתות Aggadatas which were not really you know about respect
for the תורה Torah and so on and then ספרים חיצוניים Sefarim
Chitzonim led to a whole question about בן סירא. Ben Sira. Anyway,
now we switch gears to the second part of the משנה, Mishnah,
most probably in I think printed משניות Mishnayos it's a second משנה,
Mishnah, which is about now we start to identify specific people that
don't have a portion in the World to Come. And it says
three kings and four laypeople don't have a portion in the World
to Come. And the three kings are ירבעם בן נבט, Yerovam ben
Nevat, the one who started the split with the kingdoms,
אחאב Achav who is obviously one of the most most evil kings
of Israel, אחאב Achav and איזבל Izevel and so on. Interesting איזבל
Izevel doesn't get mentioned. So much for our I think whatever equality.
Yeah exactly. So much for our our equal our you know our
so to speak and
and
where was it, excuse me,
and ירבעם, Yerovam, אחאב Achav and מנשה. Minisheh. Okay, so anyway so
now we're going to focus on that. So a lot of the
focus is going to be actually on looking at some of those
פסוקים. pesukim. So I told דבורה Dvora last night I said oh
I hate this part of פרק חלק Perek Chelek because it means
that now I have to go back and learn those sections of
תנ"ך Tanach that I totally forgot, you know I have to actually
go remember who all these kings are and everything that they did
or whatever. Okay, anyway so
שלשה מלכים וארבעה הדיוטות. Shlosha melachim v'arba hedyotos. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan
about
our story ירבעם. Yerovam. So we're going to start go one by
one ירבעם Yerovam
שריבה
עם. sheriva am. So that was so we're going to do like
a play on the word so רש"י Rashi says it basically means
it's I mean the word רובע rove'a also means like to perform
a act of like sexual penetration but here רש"י Rashi also says
it means like I don't know to trample the people. I'm not
exactly sure how he gets that. Anyway, to trample the people.
שריבה עם sheriva am דבר אחר davar acher ירבעם Yerovam שעשה מריבה
בעם. she-asah merivah ba-am. He made contentious like he split the people
in two. Okay דבר אחר davar acher ירבעם Yerovam שעשה מריבה בין
ישראל לאביהם שבשמים. she-asah merivah bein Yisrael l'avihem she-bashamayim. He distanced Israel
from their Father in heaven because he made the golden calves and
he led all the ten tribes to idolatry. That was pretty big,
so it was not only splitting the people but also what he
did with the tribes because as we're going to see remind ourselves
that actually the prophecy was was that he should split the people,
that he was doing with God's under God's through you know the
word of the prophet, but it was also the way he led
them all astray.
Okay so בן נבט, ben Nevat, so we'll play on the words
בן נבט, ben Nevat, בן שניבט ולא ראה. ben shenibat v'lo ra'ah.
He saw but he did not see. So what did he see?
He saw something as היה סבור להביט יפה. hayah savur l'habit yafeh.
He wanted but he tried to see but he didn't see. So
we're going to see a whole sort of vision that he had
and how he misinterpreted it. Okay תנא tana הוא נבט, הוא מיכה,
הוא שבע בן בכרי. hu Nevat, hu Micha, hu Sheva ben Bichri.
So נבט'ס Nevat's father is also מיכה Micha and not the prophet
מיכה, Micha, the guy of the פסל של מיכה, Pesel she-Micha, the
person who like had an idol and so on and
שבע בן בכרי. Sheva ben Bichri. נבט שניבט ולא ראה. Nevat shenibat
v'lo ra'ah. Now we're going to do explain how he has all
these
names. מיכה שנתמכמך בבנין. Micha she-nis-mach-mech b'vinyan. The story of מיכה Micha
was that רש"י Rashi quotes the מדרש Midrash which is that משה
Moshe saw all the Jewish babies that were being put built into
the structures because they didn't have the straw and they were being
forced to use these babies as bricks and משה Moshe said to
God how do you allow such a thing? And God said oh
these are all going to be רשעים resha'im anyway, the babies that
this is happening to. So משה Moshe so God just as he'll
show you. So one baby was saved and then that שנתמכמך בבנין.
she-nis-mach-mech b'vinyan. And then that baby turned out to be מיכה Micha
who was the you know who source of bringing idolatry to the
Jewish people. Who lived a thousand whatever. Anyway, what can I say,
what can I say, it's a מדרש. Midrash. All right anyway, Jews
put
the babies in the בנין? binyan?
No the I don't know the Jews, the מצרים, Mitzrim, the Jews
were forced to. Okay anyway so okay
fine let's take a look. שבע בן בכרי
שמו בבנין. Sheva ben Bichri shmo bivinyan.
I lost my place. מיכה, Micha, שבע, Sheva,
ומשמע שבע
בן בכרי שמו. umashma Sheva ben Bichri shmo. But his given name
was שבע בן בכרי. Sheva ben Bichri. Fine. תנו רבנן. Tano Rabbanan.
שלשה ניבתו ולא ראו. Shalosh nivtu velo rau. Three people saw but
didn't really see. ואלו הן: Ve-elu hein: נבט, Nevat, like my wife
always tells me, I hear but I don't
listen. תנו רבנן. Tano Rabbanan. Okay,
so נבט, Nevat, אחיתופל, Achitophel, right, the father of ירבעם, Yerovam, ואצטגניני
פרעה. ve-itztagninei Paroh. נבט, Nevat, שראה, she-ra'ah, what did he see? נבט
Nevat see. ראה אש יוצאת מאמתו. Ra'ah esh yotzes me-amato. He saw
fire coming out of like his penis. הוא סבר: Hu savar: איהו
מליך. iu malich.
So he thought somehow, I don't know, because it was fire coming
out of him and maybe it showed virility or power, it meant
that he was going to be king. ולא היא: Velo hi: ירבעם
הוא דנפיק מיניה. Yerovam hu de-nafik minei. It meant that his seed,
his descendant, his son, he would be the one that would be
king. Okay.
אחיתופל, Achitophel, what did אחיתופל Achitophel see?
ראה צרעת שזרחה לו על המטה. Ra'ah tzara'as she-zachah lo al hamatah.
So he saw leprosy or whatever there. So,
הוא סבר: Hu savar: איהו מליך. iu malich. So of course leprosy
makes me think that I'm going to be king. Again, I have
no idea, I have no nothing what to say about that. ולא
היא, Velo hi, it's not true, but rather ולא היא Velo hi
בת שבע בתו הוא דנפקא מינה. Bas-Sheva bito hu de-nafkā minah. It's
בת שבע Bas-Sheva his daughter because and not by you know, בת
שבע's Bas-Sheva son, so that's actually because if we're so, fine. Fine.
דנפיק מינה שלמה, de-nafik minah Shlomo,
that שלמה Shlomo came from her. אצטגניני פרעה, Itztagninei Paroh, פרעה's Paroh
like astrologers. What did they see? So, דאמר רבי חמא בר רבי
חנינא: de-amar Rabbi Chama bar Rabbi Chanina:
מהי דכתיב, mai dikesiv, המה מי מריבה, hemah mei Merivah,
those are the waters of contention. המה שראו אצטגניני פרעה. Hemah she-rau
itztagninei Paroh.
The astrologers of פרעה Paroh saw that these waters, you know, a
vision of water that would sort of be the downfall of משה.
Moshe. וטעו Veto and they made a mistake. ראו שמשיען של ישראל
במים הוא לוקה. Rau she-moshian shel Yisrael bamayim hu lokeh. They saw
that the savior of ישראל Yisrael would be smitten by water, would
ultimately meet his downfall by water. אמר, Amar, so that led them
to prophesy to whatever to tell פרעה, Paroh, to advise פרעה, Paroh,
כל הבן הילוד היאורה תשליכהו, kol haben hayilod haye'orah tashlichuhu, throw all
the Jewish babies into the water because that'll take care of it,
that'll whoever was going to be the savior will drown. So that's
what they misinterpreted what they saw. והן לא ידעו שעל עסקי מי
מריבה לוקה. Vehein lo yade'u she-al iskei mei Merivah lokeh. They didn't
realize it was about the waters of מי מריבה mei Merivah that
would be משה's Moshe downfall. Fine. ומנלן דלא אתי לעולם הבא? Umenalan
dlo asi l'olam haba? Fine.
So that was a little דרש drash on the word ירבעם בן
נבט Yerovam ben Nevat with a little digression. Now, now that we've
had fun with his name, how do we know he's not going
to get עולם הבא? Olam Haba? דלא אתי לעולם הבא. Dlo asi
l'olam haba. דכתיב, De-kesiv, it says, ויהי בדבר הזה לחטאת בית ירבעם
ולהכחיד ולהשמיד מעל פני האדמה. vayehi badavar hazeh l'chatas beis Yerovam ulehachid
ulehishmid mei'al pnei ha'adamah.
This matter will be for the sin of the house of ירבעם
Yerovam and to destroy them and to whatever destroy them, some other
word for destroy, from the face of the earth. להכחיד בעולם הזה,
Lehachid ba'olam hazeh, to wipe them out from this world, ולהשמיד לעולם
הבא, ulehishmid l'olam haba, and to destroy them for עולם הבא. Olam
Haba. So the double
language. אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: מפני מה זכה ירבעם למלכות?
mipnei mah zachah Yerovam lemalchus? Alright, so he was so evil, let's
try to understand, why was he the one that merited being king,
right, then after you read the story in תנך, Tanakh, like as
I said, how could he be so evil? What? Okay, but as
I said last night, if you reread the story in תנך, Tanakh,
right, he was like chosen to be from by the נביא Navi
to be the one as bringing punishment to שלמה Shlomo and so
on, to be the one that would, you know, it was actually
given as a merit to be, you know, to be the leader
of ישראל Yisrael and a punishment to שלמה. Shlomo. So he started
off presumably good. So why was he chosen? מפני שהוכיח את שלמה.
Mipnei she-hochi'ach es Shlomo.
Because he actually gave מוסר musar to שלמה Shlomo for the way
שלמה Shlomo had been acting incorrectly. So therefore, and you know, the
way the נביא Navi presents it is that שלמה Shlomo like led
the people to you know, worship idols or whatever, the פשט pshat
of the פסוקים, psukim, I mean חזל Chazal read it differently, you
know, that he brought all this idolatry into ישראל Yisrael or whatever
and as a punishment the kingdom is being divided and so ירבעם
Yerovam was the first one to actually give מוסר musar to שלמה.
Shlomo. Now, not exactly about the idolatry. ומפני מה נענש? Umipnei mah
ne'enash? So then why in the end was he punished? Now of
course you could say he was punished because in the end he
wound up being an you know, leading the people astray as you
know, and building you know, building golden calves etc. But anyway, I
guess it means like where were the seeds of that in the
original act? If his original act reflected his good qualities, where do
we what was the indication about where it was bad? You know.
Or how did he become so bad?
Right, well let's read the answer. מפני שהוכיחו ברבים. Mipnei she-hochicho berabbim.
Because even though he gave him מוסר musar and he was supposed
to give him מוסר musar and it shows that he stood for
the right thing, he also wasn't respectful at the same time and
he did it in public. So already you see that he had
these mixed qualities. To him. שנאמר, shene'emar, וזה הדבר אשר הרים יד
במלך שלמה. vezeh hadavar asher herim yad bamelech Shlomo.
This is the thing that he lifted up his hand against the
King שלמה, Shlomo, and here it sort of means that he's lifted
up his hand in terms of like he verbally remonstrated him. שלמה...
Shlomo... שהרים יד במלך, sheherim yad bamelech, excuse me,
he lifted up his hand against the king. שלמה בנה את המלוא
סגר את הפרץ עיר דוד. Shlomo bana et Hamillo sagar et haperetz
ir David.
שלמה Shlomo built the exposure, he closed the, you know, the breach
in the city of דוד. David. That doesn't sound like a bad
thing to be doing. So אמר לו, amar lo, so ירבעם Yaravam
says to שלמה: Shlomo: דוד אביך פרץ פרצות בחומה, David avicha paratz
pratzot bachomah,
your father דוד David intentionally made there to be wide openings in
the wall of ירושלים Yerushalayim כדי שיעלו ישראל לרגל, kedei sheya'alu Yisrael
laregel,
that in order to make it that all these different ways of
accessing ירושלים Yerushalayim and coming into all these open door policy. ואתה
גדרת אותם, ve'atah gadarta otam,
you closed them all. Why? כדי לעשות אנגריא לבת פרעה, kedei la'asot
angarya lebat Paroh,
in order to make אנגריא angarya which is sort of like a
king's service to בת פרעה. bat Paroh. What does that mean? So
רש״י Rashi says what it means is that you closed up the
walls, you put in gates, and you installed like tolls at the
gates so that everybody if they wanted to come in would have
to pay a fee, and that was in order to, in order
to increase the queen's revenue, you know, or to do something to
bring glory to your queen there who is the daughter of פרעה.
Paroh. ומאי וזה אשר הרים יד במלך? umai vezeh asher herim yad
bamelech?
So how do you check the literal words of אשר הרים יד?
asher herim yad? הרים יד herim yad also sounds more defiant and
noxious. I mean here it sounds the way the גמרא Gemara is
reading it as a positive thing, he gave him good מוסר. mussar.
So אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, שחלץ תפיליו בפניו. shechalatz tfilav
befanav. So he lifted up his hand to take off his תפילין.
tfilin. That's הרים יד? herim yad? No, that wasn't a rebellion, that's
just reading that פסוק, pasuk, okay, and that's a disrespect somehow. Not
exactly clear why that's so disrespectful, exposing yourself, it's like a little
bit of an act of undressing. Okay, so already there were good
things about this, the גמרא Gemara is reading, this is not yet
the splitting off. The splitting off happened after שלמה Shlomo died with
the son רחבעם, Rechavam, okay, but this is already showing some good
qualities and bad qualities. אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, גסות רוח
שהיה בו בירבעם טרדתו מן העולם. gasut ruach shehayah bo beYaravam tardato
min ha'olam.
The sort of arrogance because maybe this aspect that he was willing
to talk against the king in public, I mean that's real arrogance,
right? And taking off the תפילין, tfilin, again doing stuff that you're
not like, you know, the way you're dressing or undressing or whatever,
you know, that shows that disrespect and arrogance. And that ultimately were
the seeds of what led him to really go astray in the
future, cause you know, he went astray by, we'll see, by making
these golden calves. But what was that about? It was ultimately all
tied into his arrogance. Okay. So גסות הרוח טרדתו מן העולם, gasut
haruach tardato min ha'olam, that led,
that destroyed him from the world and also עולם olam here is
עולם הבא. olam haba. שנאמר ויאמר ירבעם בלבו. shene'emar vayomer Yaravam belibo.
So he said in his heart עתה תשוב הממלכה לבית דוד אם
יעלה העם הזה לעשות זבחים בבית ה׳ בירושלים. atah tashuv hamamlachah leveit
David im ya'aleh ha'am hazeh la'asot zvachim beveit Hashem biYerushalayim. And then
the irony too because we're saying that the way he gave מוסר
mussar to שלמה Shlomo was to preventing the people from doing עליה
לרגל, aliyah laregel, right? It's purposefully ironic, right? And then his concern
was that if he doesn't create a different center, a different religious
center, then everybody three times a year is going to go to
ירושלים Yerushalayim and do עליה לרגל, aliyah laregel, and it's going to
be all very clear that he's not going to be able to
maintain a separate kingdom, right? Because ultimately their religious center is going
to be in יהודה Yehudah and it's going to be in ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. That's very explicit in the פסוקים, psukim, okay? So therefore, where
was it, לעשות זבחים בבית ה׳ בירושלים ושב לב העם הזה אל
אדוניהם אל רחבעם מלך יהודה. la'asot zvachim beveit Hashem biYerushalayim veshav lev
ha'am hazeh el adoneihem el Rechavam melech Yehudah. In the end, they'll
switch their allegiance back to רחבעם, Rechavam, right? Why should we worship
a king there when our religious center is elsewhere? והרגוני ושבו אל
רחבעם מלך יהודה. veharaguni veshavu el Rechavam melech Yehudah.
So therefore that's because, because he wanted to maintain his power and
his status, that ultimately led him to make these golden calves and
to, so to create a new religious center, an idolatrous religious center
in ישראל Yisrael as opposed to יהודה. Yehudah. Okay, אמר, amar, he
said, גמירי, gemiri, that אין עמידה בעזרה אלא למלכי בית יהודה בלבד.
ein amidah ba'azarah ela lemalchei beit Yehudah bilvad. Now the גמרא Gemara
is going to add a line. Like, well maybe I can go
with them to ירושלים Yerushalayim and I will also show my kingdom.
Of course, it's not in your country anymore. But here the גמרא
Gemara is going to add another dynamic. גמירי, gemiri, we have a
tradition
that the only people who get to sit in the עזרה azarah
in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash are kings who are descendants of
יהודה. Yehudah. So it's not just they'll go to the religious center
in יהודה, Yehudah, but they'll see the status that the king there
has and that's greater than my status. כיון דחזו ליה לרחבעם דיתיב
ואנא קאימנא, keivan dechazu leh leRechavam deyativ ve'ana ka'imna, they'll see רחבעם
Rechavam sitting and I have to stand, סברי האי מלכא והאי עבדא,
savrei hai malka vehai avda,
this one is the king, the other one is the servant. ואי
יתיבנא, ve'i yativna, so maybe I should go with them and sit
as well to show that I'm equal to רחבעם, Rechavam, so then
מורד במלכות הוי, mored bemalchut havei, it's interesting, they don't say by
sitting in the עזרה azarah you'll be doing something that would be
against the sanctity... sanctity of the עזרה. Azarah. We interpret it as
rebelling against the king. But how have you a Yerovam מורד במלכות?
mored bemalchut? You're already are setting up a different kingdom. I find
very strange the use of the word מורד במלכות. mored bemalchut. Because
מורד במלכות mored bemalchut was when he when he did a civil
war whatever when he broke the kingdom into two. So okay so
I mean it's more מורד mored in the special status that מלכי
יהודה Malchei Yehuda have. It's a very interesting sort of phrase. Anyway
מורד במלכות mored bemalchut maybe it means God's מלכות malchut but that
would be an interesting use of the phrase. Okay וקטלינן ליה vekatlinan
lei anyway it's just so open in front of him. Right
yeah maybe it's one thing you're right to have a different מלכות
malchut somebody else somewhere else but especially when you're on the king
when you're in his territory and you're showing that you don't respect
his authority yeah you're probably right that probably is the meaning. Still
funny the phrase מורד במלכות. mored bemalchut. Anyway וקטלינן ליה vekatlinan lei
they'll kill me and ואזלי בתריה veazli batrei and anyway they'll then
they'll follow Rechavam.
So anyway I can't have them again it's interesting they had to
frame it this way because clearly you're going to a different a
different kingdom for your religious center. Anyway but it won't just be
they'll go there they'll see that he's more of a king than
I am. מיד ויואץ המלך ויעש שני עגלי זהב miyad vayiva'atz hamelech
vaya'as shenei eglei zahav so he took advice and he made these
two golden calves. ויאמר אליהם רב לכם מעלות ירושלים vayomer aleihem rav
lachem mealot Yerushalayim no it's too much to shlep to ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
הנה אלוהיך ישראל אשר העלוך מארץ מצרים hineh elohecha Yisrael asher he'elucha
me'eretz Mitzrayim obviously echoing the פסוק pasuk by the other עגל הזהב
eigel hazahav the first עגל הזהב. eigel hazahav. וישם את האחד בבית
אל ואת האחד נתן בדן vayasem et ha'echad beVeit El ve'et ha'echad
natan beDan and he put them in בית אל Beit El and
דן Dan so also it would be easily it would be convenient
why shlep all the way to ירושלים Yerushalayim I'll even make two
two places you can go. Okay anyway so that shows that it
was his גסות הרוח gasut haruach and again the irony that originally
he gave מוסר mussar because of you're not making it easy for
the people to be עולה לרגל oleh laregel and then his whole
break his whole thing but anyway was but the fact that he
was able to do it like defiantly he gave מוסר mussar to
שלמה Shlomo was that גסות הרוח gasut haruach that ultimately made him
do anything he could to retain power and status that ultimately created
the you know turned it into a idolatrous country where the center
was these places of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Okay so מאי ויואץ
mai vayiva'atz what does it mean that he like took advice? So
אמר רבי יהודה שהושיב רשע אצל צדיק. amar Rabbi Yehuda shehoshiv rasha
etzel tzadik. Here's how he got the people to follow him. He
took a wicked person and a righteous person. אמר
להו amar lehu and he went around to get a sign a
you know sign a what's it called a petition not a petition
but anyway you know everybody to sign off and to recognize
his
authority as king everybody in you know the ten tribes. So אמר
להו amar lehu he would tell them חתמיתו chatmitu
sign this document על כל דעבידנא al kol de'avidna that you're that
you're going to follow everything I do.
אמרו ליה הין amru lei hin they said yes. אמר להו amar
lehu he said to them מלכא בעינא למהוי malka be'ina lemehavei
I want to be king are you going will you sign off
on it? אמרו ליה הין amru lei hin they said yes. כל
דאמינא לכו עבידיתו kol de'amina lachon aviditu will you do everything I
tell you? אמרו ליה הין amru lei hin they said to him
yes. אפילו למיפלח לעבודת כוכבים afilu lemiflach la'avodat kochavim would you listen
to me so far to be עובד עבודה זרה? oved avoda zara?
אמר ליה צדיק amar lei tzadik so the צדיק tzadik says חס
ושלום chas veshalom
God forbid! אמר ליה רשע לצדיק amar lei rasha latzadik so the
רשע rasha said to the צדיק tzadik סלקא דעתך דגברא כירובעם פלח
לעבודת
כוכבים salka datchach degavrah keYerovam palach la'avodat kochavim you think I mean
Yerovam was very righteous initially you think somebody as righteous as him
would really want to be עובד עבודה זרה? oved avoda zara? אלא
למינסיוהו הוא דקבעי ela leminseyuhu hu dekabei
he's testing us he just wants to see if we're going to
say we'll follow him through thick and thin. He's not being literal
about חס ושלום chas veshalom of course he wouldn't be עובד עבודה
זרה. oved avoda zara. וקבילתון למימריה vekabiltun lemeimreih
he's testing us just to see if we're going to accept his
authority. Okay and therefore the רשע rasha got the צדיק tzadik to
sign on. And by the end of the day he got everybody
in the country to sign on that they would follow him and
even to be עובד עבודה זרה. oved avoda zara. Exactly exactly so
he got the הסכמות. haskamos. Exactly exactly ואף אחיה השילוני טעה וחתם
ve'af Achiya HaShiloni ta'ah vechatam
and even אחיה השילוני Achiya HaShiloni signed it okay because as we
will see because well well we'll see the story okay. דהא יהוא
צדיקא רבא הוה deha Yehu tzadikah rabbah havah so
here's the proof that אחיה השילוני Achiya HaShiloni was this the righteous
you know נביא navi or whatever that how he actually managed to
also be tricked and sign on. Okay דהא יהוא צדיקא רבא הוה
deha Yehu tzadikah rabbah havah how do we know he did he
did that how do you know אחיה השילוני Achiya HaShiloni signed on?
Because יהוא Yehu we're going to infer it from a story about
יהוא. Yehu. יהוא Yehu was a great צדיק tzadik okay and here's
another story about a צדיק tzadik who went astray. יהוא Yehu this
is later in the story of the history of the kings where
you know אחאב Achav who's the next evil king we're going to
deal with so God appoints יהוא Yehu as a the king to
come up after אחאב Achav and to follow God's words and then
he wipes out the whole house of אחאב Achav following the sort
of prophecy and following the נבואה nevuah and the you know the
direction he got from God and then after he wipes out the
whole house of אחאב Achav which is what he was supposed to
do then he also turns to do evil.
Okay דהא יהוא צדיקא רבא הוה deha Yehu tzadikah rabbah havah he
started off as a very righteous person שנאמר ויאמר ה' אל יהוא
יען אשר הטיבות לעשות הישר shene'emar vayomer Hashem el Yehu ya'an asher
hetivota la'asot hayashar בעיני. be'einai.
You did the good in my eyes. ככל אשר בלבבי עשית. kichol
asher bilvavi asita. You did all that was good in my eye,
all in my heart, everything I asked you to do. לבית אחאב,
leveit Achav, you wiped out the whole house of אחאב. Achav. So
therefore בני רביעיים ישבו לך על כיסא ישראל, benei revi'iyim yeshvu lach
al kisse Yisrael, even your fourth generation will be kings of Israel.
וכתיב uch'tiv ויהוא לא שמר ללכת בתורת ה' אלוהי
ישראל. veYehu lo shamar lalechet beTorat Hashem Elohei Yisrael. And afterwards, right
as he, he himself went astray בכל לבבו לא סר מחטאת ירבעם
bechol levavo lo sar mechatat Yerovam
and he followed all the sins of ירבעם. Yerovam. Now it's very
interesting, right? Because here he was, he just wiped out אחאב, Achav,
you might want to say he followed in the footsteps of אחאב.
Achav. So so many different evil kings of ישראל Yisrael and the
גמרא's Gemara going to note this later, when it speaks about how
they were evil and idolaters or whatever, they say they followed ירבעם
Yerovam because he was the paradigm. Well, he was the base, he
was the first. But now the גמרא Gemara is going to connect
it specifically to the sin of ירבעם, Yerovam, particularly here, because he
started off as a righteous king. How did this person who started
off so righteously now turn astray? Okay? So אשר החטיא את ישראל,
asher hecheti et Yisrael, ירבעם Yerovam who made the people sin. מאי
גרמיה, mai garmeh, what caused him to sin? To also go worship
idolatry, יהוא? Yehu? Now we're talking about, אמר אביי, amar Abaye, ברית
כרותה לשפתים, berit keruta lasfatayim, a covenant is made with the lips.
It's because his speech, he was caught by his own speech. How
was that? שנאמר shenemar because he said, because this is what he
was doing, after he wiped out the house of אחאב, Achav, he
wanted to now wipe out all the prophets of the בעל. Ba'al.
Okay? And the way he was able to identify all the prophets
of the בעל Ba'al was he tricked the people. He made it
sound like he wanted to worship the בעל Ba'al and called all
the prophets to him and then he wiped them all out. That's
the story. Okay? שנאמר shenemar he got up and he said אחאב
עבד הבעל מעט, Achav avad haBa'al me'at,
אחאב Achav was a פישער pisher when it came to serving the
בעל. Ba'al. Okay? יהוא יעבדנו הרבה, Yehu ya'avdenu harbe, I'm going to
really worship him. All right? And then he got all the prophets
to come to him and then he wiped them out. Okay? So
אביי Abaye said, "Ah, but since he said יהוא יעבדנו הרבה, Yehu
ya'avdenu harbe, so because those words came out of his lips, he
somehow, they somehow had power over him and that ultimately led him
astray." You have to be very careful with what you say. רבא
אמר, Rava amar, no, and this gets back to our earlier point.
חותמתו של אחיה השילוני ראה וטעה. chotamto shel Achiya haShiloni ra'a veta'a.
Okay? No, he saw the signature of אחיה השילוני, Achiya haShiloni, אחיה?
Achiya? I said אחיה, Achiya, אחיה השילוני, Achiya haShiloni, and that's what
led him astray. If even אחיה השילוני Achiya haShiloni signed off to
follow ירבעם Yerovam and to follow him in עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
it must be that that's the right thing to do. Okay? So
that ties back to our point about how deceitful ירבעם Yerovam was,
how he got everybody to sign off and even the most righteous
people got signed off and that ultimately also then led יהוא Yehu
astray. So that ties in. יהוא Yehu followed in the footsteps of
ירבעם. Yerovam. He saw the document that everybody had signed off on
ירבעם Yerovam and even the most righteous and ultimately that led him
astray as well. Okay.
So that was him following the signature of אחיה השילוני. Achiya haShiloni.
Now,
the ב"ח Bach here takes out the word or the דרא Dra
takes out the whole word דכתיב. dechitiv. The ב"ח Bach just takes
out the letter ד, dalet, because when דכתיב dechitiv means we're going
to now support what we just said and we're really not supporting
what we just said, we're really moving on to a new topic.
So the ב"ח Bach just takes out one letter. כתיב, ktiv, it's
written. ושחטה שטים העמיקו, veshachata shetim he'emiku, and the slaughtered or whatever,
the those that went astray went deep, or whatever, what the heck
does that mean? ואני מוסר לכולם, va'ani musar lechulam, and I am
a reproof to all of them. So it's a very difficult פסוק.
pasuk. So אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא,
amar haKadosh Baruch Hu, הן, hen, so now we're talking about the
sin of
ירבעם. Yerovam. הן hen העמיקו משלי, he'emiku misheli, they went deeper than
me. Okay? So שטים, shetim, those that went astray, הם העמיקו, hem
he'emiku, they went deeper than I went and ושחטה veshachata here is
like to be offering, slaughtering sacrifices to עבודה זרה avodah zarah or
to be willing to kill people. What does that mean? אני אמרתי,
ani amarti, כל שאינו עולה לרגל, kol she'eino oleh laregel, עובר בעשה.
over be'aseh. I only gave a little bit of punishment, I said
if you're not עולה לרגל, oleh laregel, you transgress a positive commandment.
והן אמרו, vehen amru, כל העולה לרגל, kol ha'oleh laregel, ידקר בחרב.
yidaker becherev.
And they said, whoever goes up to the Temple will be cut
down by the sword, pierced by the sword. That was what ירבעם
Yerovam says. So they slaughtered because they went astray, you know, and
went deeper than I went. Okay?
So, you know, so in terms of preventing people from being עולה
לרגל. oleh laregel.
What's this ואני מוסר לכולם? va'ani moseir lechulam?
So רש"י Rashi reads it, you know, I only gave them like
יסורים yisurim if they would not be עולה לרגל oleh laregel and
they were willing to kill people for being עולה לרגל. oleh laregel.
Okay. ויהי בעת ההיא, vayehi ba'et hahi, וירבעם יצא מירושלים. veYerovam yatza
miYerushalayim. Now back to the actual story. ירבעם Yerovam went out from
Jerusalem. So this was before, this was when he was still like
a, you know, a servant of שלמה, Shlomo, well servant, whatever, an
officer for שלמה, Shlomo, and now he was being approached by the
נביא, navi, this is the נביא navi אחיה השילוני Achiya haShiloni who
we said eventually he got to sign up to tell him that
he would split the kingdom in two. Okay, וימצאו אותו אחיה השילוני
הנביא. Veyimtz'o oto Achiya Hashiloni hanavi. So אחיה השילוני Achiya Hashiloni
the prophet who we mentioned earlier saw him בדרך. baderech. והוא מתכסה
בשמלה חדשה. Vehu mitkaseh besimlah chadashah. אחיה Achiya was wearing a new
cloak. The significance of the new cloak is that אחיה Achiya cuts
it up into ten, into twelve strips and tells ירבעם Yerovam take
ten of the twelve strips. Then he says this is a sign
that you will take ten of the twelve tribes and you will
be king over ten of the twelve tribes. Okay, תנא משמיה דרבי
יוסי. Tana mishmei deRabbi Yosi. So what does it mean עת היא?
et hi? Why at that time? What's special about that time? So
where were we? עת היא מזומנת לפורענות. Et hi mezumenet lepuranut. It
was at
that time has always was a special time that was designated for
bad things to happen. Okay, this Gemara's idea which it's now going
to deal with, right? That there are some times like תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av is the best example, which just bad, gonna be a
time when bad things are going to happen. So that was one
of those times. ובעת פקודתם יאבדו. Uve'et pekudatam yovedu.
At the time when I will visit upon them, when I visit
upon them their sin, they will be destroyed. תנא משמיה דרבי יוסי,
Tana mishmei deRabbi Yosi, עת מזומנת לפורענות. et mezumenet lepuranut. It's not
just a random time, it's a time that specifically is designated for
bad things to happen. ובעת רצון עניתיך. Uve'et ratzon aniticha. There's also
good times. At a time of desire I will respond to you.
תנא משמיה דרבי יוסי, Tana mishmei deRabbi Yosi, עת מזומנת לטובה. et
mezumenet letovah. That's a specific time. So it'd be nice to know
what times of the year this is. Okay, but those are not
just at the chance time, but no, at those times of אלול
Elul maybe, okay? Right? Like God is close to us during אלול,
Elul, like we have the idea there are times of the year
which are more good things happen or bad things happen. Yes.
It's not like a historical time for
what? This era, the 40s, the 30s?
I don't think so because, well, you because, maybe, but if you
look at the next פסוק, pasuk, okay? וביום פקדי ופקדתי עליהם חטאתם,
Uveyom pokdi ufakadeti aleihem chatatam,
right? At the time when I will visit upon them I will
visit their sin. This is by the חטא העגל, cheit ha'eigel, right?
And the עגל eigel obviously connects also to ירבעם. Yerovam. תנא משמיה
דרבי יוסי, Tana mishmei deRabbi Yosi, עת היא מזומנת לפורענות. et hi
mezumenet lepuranut. Okay?
So again that particularly we spoke about, you know, the חטא העגל
cheit ha'eigel and tying into, you know, that if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, what does רש"י Rashi say? Let's see
that one. וביום פקדי בתשעה באב שבכל השנה מימות המרגלים שנגזרה בו
גזירה יום מזומן לפורענות בו חזרו המרגלים בו נחרב הבית בחרבנה ראשונה
ובשנייה. Uveyom pokdi beTisha B'Av shebechol hashanah miyemot hameraglim shengizrah bo gezeirah
yom mezuman lepuranut bo chazru hameraglim bo necherav habayit becharvanah rishonah uveshniyah.
So רש"י Rashi certainly as this one means that it's a recurring
time.
Okay. So ויהי בעת ההיא וירד יהודה מאת אחיו. Vayehi ba'et hahi
vayered Yehudah me'et echav. At that time יהודה Yehudah descended from his
brothers. תנא משמיה דרבי יוסי, Tana mishmei deRabbi Yosi, עת היא מזומנת
לפורענות. et hi mezumenet lepuranut. That's interesting because that's not bad things
happening yet, right?
His sons die first though.
Yeah, but it's also it's at a very personal level. All these
other things were at a national level and his two sons dying
didn't happen at the moment that he left. I mean that took
a while, right? I mean he you know, I mean it was
the beginning of a long process. It's a little different than the
others. Okay, now moving back to the whole story. וילך רחבעם שכם.
Vayelech Rechavam Shechem. He went to שכם. Shechem. And כי שכם בא
כל ישראל להמליך אותו. ki Shechem ba kol Yisrael lehamlich oto. So
this is רחבעם, Rechavam, not ירבעם. Yerovam. So רחבעם Rechavam had gone
to שכם Shechem because they were going to now make him king
in שכם Shechem after שלמה. Shlomo. רחבעם Rechavam was שלמה's Shlomo son.
תנא משמיה דרבי יוסי, Tana mishmei deRabbi Yosi, now similar רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi was talking about times and here again you'll see that
we're talking about like recurring the same way recurring time, specific places
that are always gonna be bad places. Okay. So same רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi here. תנא משמיה דרבי
יוסי, Tana mishmei deRabbi Yosi, מקום מזומן לפורענות. makom mezuman lepuranut. Yeah,
שכם's Shechem a bad place. בשכם עינו את דינה. BeShechem inu et
Dinah. שכם Shechem is where דינה Dinah was raped. בשכם מכרו אחיו
את יוסף, BeShechem macharu echav et Yosef, etc. That's where they sold
יוסף. Yosef. Now of course יוסף Yosef went to שכם. Shechem. הלא
אחיך רועים בשכם. Halo achecha ro'im beShechem. And then he had to
follow them to דותן. Dotan. But רש"י Rashi says alright, דותן Dotan
was some suburb, it was still basically in שכם. Shechem. Alright, anyway.
בשכם נחלקה
מלכות בית דוד. BeShechem nechelkah malchut beit David. That was the place
that the kingdom of בית דוד beit David divided. So that is
a place where bad things happen. וירבעם יצא מירושלים. VeYerovam yatza miYerushalayim.
ירבעם Yerovam left
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא, Amar Rabbi Chanina bar Papa,
שיצא מפתקה של ירושלים. sheyatza miptakah shel Yerushalayim. Who left the sort
of you know the faith of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. The פתק, petek, you
know, is like you know like a like a little like message
on a piece of paper or whatever. So he left sort of
that you know their faith, their גורל. goral. Okay.
It's a unique usage of the word.
I mean you don't see that that often, do you? Like it's...
Yeah I know רש"י Rashi sort of connects it to the idea
but yes. Not when by like the little piece of paper falls
from heaven that says you
know anyway. So it means like the faith of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. וימצאו
אותו אחיה השילוני הנביא בדרך. Veyimtz'o oto Achiya Hashiloni hanavi baderech. והוא
מתכסה בשלמה חדשה. Vehu mitkaseh besalmah chadashah. Going back to this. So
אחיה השילוני Achiya Hashiloni was wearing a new cloak. ושניהם לבדם בשדה.
Usheneihem levadam basadeh. They were alone in the field and again the
story is he ripped the cloak into
twelve strips and said you take ten and you know those are
the ten tribes.
Okay. מאי בשלמה חדשה? Mai besalmah chadashah? What does it mean the
new cloak? אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, כשלמה חדשה. kesalmah chadashah.
מה שלמה חדשה? mah salmah chadashah? Like a new cloak. אין בה
שום דופי ein ba shum dofi the same way a brand new
piece of clothing doesn't yet have any imperfections or any stains, you
know, it's perfect. אף תורתו של ירבעם לא היה בה שום דופי.
Af Torato shel Yeravam lo haya ba shum dofi. So now it's
how great ירבעם Yeravam was before he was he himself went astray.
He, his level of Torah was perfect. Okay, not his צדקות, tzidkus,
now we're talking about his Torah. Okay, דבר אחר davar acher שלמה
חדשה salma hachadasha
שחידשו דברים שלא שמעה אוזן מעולם. shechidshu devarim shelo shamah ozen me'olam.
It was a new cloak, the Torah they went... right, you think
they went straight to talk about politics? No, first they spent time
learning Torah before he came along to talk to him about the
civil, about dividing up the kingdom. And they learned Torah, the Torah
they learned was like a new garment, nobody had ever heard that,
it was so brilliant and innovative. ויהיו שניהם לבדם בשדה. Vayihyu shneihem
levadam basadeh. What does it mean they were alone in the field?
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav שכל תלמידי
חכמים... shekol talmidei chachamim... back to the idea that they were spending
their time learning Torah. שכל תלמידי חכמים דומים לפניהם כעשבי השדה. Shekol
talmidei chachamim domim lifneihem k'isvei hasadeh. They were such a different level
than other Torah scholars of their age that they were like human
beings and everybody else was like grass in their presence. ואיכא דאמרי,
V'ika d'amri, some say, שכל טעמי תורה מגולים להם כשדה. shekol ta'amei
Torah megulim lahem kasadeh. All of the hidden secrets of the Torah
was revealed to them as open to them as the grass on
the field. Okay,
now skipping to a different פסוק pasuk but which we're going to
tie in, a פסוק pasuk here by מיכה, Micha, very also like
a dense one. לכן תתני שלוחים על מורשת גת, Lachen titni shilluchim
al Moreshet Gat, therefore give messengers of like of goodbye messenger, you
know, messages of a farewell to מורשת גת. Moreshet Gat. בתי אכזיב
לאכזב למלכי ישראל. Batei Achziv l'achzav l'malchei Yisrael. The houses of אכזיב
Achziv to become a like a אכזב achzav will be like no
longer like a dried up spring as one way of reading it.
So what does that mean? למלכי ישראל l'malchei Yisrael. for the kings
of Israel. אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא Amar Rabbi Chanina bar Papa
יצאה בת קול ואמרה להם Yatza bat kol v'amra lahem מי שהרג
את הפלשתי mi sheharag et haPlishti שוב והורישכם גת, shov v'horishchem Gat,
so this is מורשת גת. Moreshet Gat. The one, King David, who
killed the Philistines and therefore through him you inherited Gat, right, because
he was גלית מגת, Golyat miGat, Goliath was from Gat. תתנו שלוחים
לבניו? titnu shilluchim l'vanav? You'll give like a like a farewell, like
a like you'll send away his kids? You'll, you know, steal the
kingdom from him? That's like you know, damned if you do, damned
if you don't. The prophet told him that this was his fate,
right? And now he's saying, so how could you do this to
King David? You know, the great King David, you're now going to
sort of give him his note of dismissal, his children? Okay, לבניו.
l'vanav. בתי אכזיב לאכזב Batei Achziv l'achzav למלכי ישראל. l'malchei Yisrael So
Rashi says it means like you are going to do deceit or
like you know
ingratitude, you know, Rashi says if you look at the bottom Rashi
on the right hand column למלכי בית דוד אתם מכזבים l'malchei Beit
David atem mechazvim like lying ואלכתם אחרי מלכי ישראל. v'halachtem acharei malchei
Yisrael. So that's בתי אכזיב Batei Achziv to lie or to or
to betray, you know, to and to follow מלכי ישראל. malchei Yisrael.
ויהיו הצדונים סרים לאכזב, V'yihyu hatzidonim sarim l'achzav, therefore let them be
given over to לכזב l'chazav to the non-Jews ביד עובדי כוכבים שהם
כפתי כזב b'yad ovdei chochavim shehem k'fatai kazav that follow after falseness.
Right, so anyway.
אמר רב שימי בר פפא
Amar Rav Shimi
bar
Papa כל הנהנה מן העולם הזה בלא ברכה. kol ha'neheneh min ha'olam
hazeh belo bracha.
So, so interesting, right,
so in here he's being, the way the Gemara is reading this,
he's being remonstrated for doing not for, I mean obviously the big
sin was the golden calves, but he's being remonstrated for just following
what the נביא navi said to him. That itself was like an
act of betrayal even though it was exactly what he was supposed
to do. Okay, אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא Amar Rabbi Chanina bar
Papa כל הנהנה מן העולם הזה בלא ברכה kol ha'neheneh min ha'olam
hazeh belo bracha כאילו גוזל להקדוש ברוך הוא וכנסת ישראל. k'ilu gozel
l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu u'Knesset Yisrael. So it's not exactly clear what how
this is relevant, okay, but he says anybody who well it is,
we'll see how it's relevant in a minute because it's going to
tie it into ירבעם. Yeravam. Okay, but anyway, anybody who eats, gets
any benefit from this world without a blessing steals God and the
Jewish people. שנאמר Shene'emar גוזל אביו ואמו, gozel aviv v'imo, one who
steals from his father and mother
ואומר אין פשע, v'omer ein pasha, and says it's no sin,
חבר הוא לאיש משחית, chaver hu l'ish mashchit, that person is
a colleague to a destructive man.
ואין אביו אלא הקדוש
ברוך הוא,
v'ein aviv ela
Hakadosh
Baruch Hu, father is
God שנאמר shene'emar הלוא הוא אביך קנך. halo hu avicha kanecha. ואין
אמו אלא כנסת ישראל, v'ein imo ela Knesset Yisrael, and mother is
the
Jewish people שנאמר shene'emar שמע בני מוסר אביך ואל תטוש תורת אמך.
shma beni musar avicha v'al titosh Torat imecha. The Torah of
your mother which is you know, so the Torah of the people.
So מה mai now by the way, you have to understand it's
a it's a funny proof text because this passage just describes what?
What is the consequence of somebody who steals from his mother and
father? It doesn't connect the dots, it doesn't explain how you know
that somebody who benefits from this world without making a ברכה bracha
is stealing from his... mother and father. The פסוק *pasuk* just describes
what is the fate or what is the significance of somebody who
steals from the mother and the father. And anyway, what's the mother
doing here? The father is easy to understand, right? The whole world
is God. If you don't make a ברכה *bracha*, then you're sort
of like taking without acknowledgment and you're stealing from God. So stealing
from the father you get. Where's the stealing from the mother? What
are you stealing from כנסת ישראל *Knesset Yisrael*? Are you stealing the
fact that like, if you give a blessing then we'll be blessed?
So by not acknowledging that this is of the blessings that God
has given us, then you're just going to bring bad stuff upon
us as a people? Like how it's stealing from the Jewish people
is not very clear here. Anyway, so it's not a great proof
text to connect the dots to the issue of a ברכה *bracha*
and נהנה מן העולם הזה *neheneh min haolam hazeh*, but anyway the
relevance for us, but it describes how terrible it is to steal
from the mother and the father. And the relevance is the end
of the פסוק *pasuk* where it says, חבר הוא לאיש משחית *Chover
hu le'ish mashchit*. What does it mean he's a colleague for a
destructive person? חבר הוא לירבעם בן נבט שהשחית ישראל לאביהם שבשמים *Chover
hu le'Yerovam ben Nevat she'hishchit Yisrael le'avihem shebashamayim*. He is like a
he's like following in the footsteps of ירבעם Yerovam, בן נבט *Yerovam
ben Nevat* that destroyed the people. Now destroyed what? You could say
he destroyed the country, he split the country in two. But no,
separated the people from God. So then it's really bad, right? If
you don't make a ברכה *bracha*, it's like you basically what did
ירבעם Yerovam *Yerovam* do to separate the people from God? He put
up these golden calves. So that's pretty bad. It's like you're עובד
עבודה זרה avodah zarah. *oved avodah zarah*. But you sort of understand
it, right? Because it's not just sometimes when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
wants to say something bad, it's like you're כאילו עובד עבודה זרה
avodah zarah. *ke'ilu oved avodah zarah*, right? But this is different, this
is sort of saying you're separating the people from God, right? So
the same way עבודה זרה avodah zarah. *avodah zarah* becomes a different
focus of worship and it takes people's worship and recognition of God
away, right, not making a ברכה *bracha* like our opportunity in this
world to sort of connect to God, and especially you understand that
a lot of the way people explain a lot of the whole
thing of the beginning of מסכת ברכות *Masechet Berachot* is how do
we connect to God when there's no בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit
HaMikdash*, right? So there's no central place of worship. But what we
connect to God through דאוונען *davening*, through ברכות *berachot*, which is why
when you take benefit from this world without making a ברכה *bracha*,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it's כאילו מעל *ke'ilu ma'al*, like you
trespassed, like you benefited from the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, right, without
incorrectly. So there's a whole sense there of connecting to God without
this בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* and center of worship. So now our
primary way of doing that, right, is through these ברכות *berachot*. ברכות
*berachot* are where sort of encountering the world and seeing God in
the world. So if you're refusing to make those ברכות *berachot*, then
you're like making, you know, it's like ירבעם Yerovam *Yerovam*, you're sort
of saying don't see God, don't worship God in the בית המקדש
*Beit HaMikdash*, worship these calves. Okay? So don't see God in the
natural world, just think it's all nature. Right? So we're creating these
like idols and these things that separate us from our God in
heaven. So you it's a very, you sort of really understand the
parallel. And maybe that's also the כנסת ישראל *Knesset Yisrael* idea, right?
That maybe, you know, it's again, the same way ירבעם Yerovam. *Yerovam*
did it and it led the people astray, you know, who knows?
Other people will learn from your example and you'll also sort of
like lead the people astray and stop recognizing God, you know, in
the way we encounter the world. Okay. So that's that. So now
the גמרא gemara. *Gemara* says, וידח ירבעם Yerovam את ישראל מאחרי השם
*Vayidach Yerovam et Yisrael me'acharei Hashem*, back to the story, וידח ירבעם
Yerovam. את ישראל מאחרי השם *Vayidach Yerovam et Yisrael me'acharei Hashem*, that
he pushed him away from God, והחטיאם חטאה גדולה *vehichti'am chata'ah gedolah*,
and made them sin a great sin. אמר amar, רבי חנין *Amar
Rabbi Chanin*, כשתי מקלות המתיזה זו את זו *kishtei maklot hamatizah zo
et zo*, like two sticks, one when you hit one another. There
is some game like this. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* describes this, but I
think I know there is some sport like this. You have a
stick and like hit it with another stick and to see how
far you can hit the stick.
Anyway, that's the image, like he separated them so far, like you
hit a stick and it goes flying, like it's not it's not
like a little separation, huge gap. Again, maybe there's something more with
that violent imagery also that we're sort of using that to describe
it. ודי זהב *Ve-Di Zahav*. Okay, so now that we talked about
the עגלים *agalim* of ירבעם Yerovam. *Yerovam*, although we only barely have
mentioned the עגלים *agalim*, anyway we're going to go back and talk
about the עגל הזהב egel hazahav. *egel hazahav* by משה *Moshe*. אמרו
דבי רבי ינאי *Amru d'vei Rabbi Yannai*, אמר amar, משה לפני הקדוש
ברוך הוא *amar Moshe lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu*, רבונו של עולם בשביל
כסף וזהב *Ribono shel olam bishvil kessef vezahav*, right? That's by in
the beginning of דברים *Devarim*. משה *Moshe* is talking about where they
went and it says they went to this place called ודי זהב
*Ve-Di Zahav*. There's no place called ודי זהב *Ve-Di Zahav*. So the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* so the דרשה *derasha* is די זהב *dai zahav*.
It was too much gold you gave them. Okay. So משה *Moshe*
said to God, רבונו של עולם בשביל כסף וזהב שהשפעת להם לישראל
*Ribono shel olam bishvil kessef vezahav she'hishpata lahem leYisrael*, because of all
the gold and silver that you poured onto the Jewish people, עד
שיאמרו די *ad she'yomru dai*, they said enough, enough already, גרם להם
לעשות להם אלהי זהב *garam lahem la'asot lahem elohei zahav*. That's what
led them to make the golden calves. They had it too easy.
משל אין ארי דורס *Mashal ein ari dores* and they had too
much gold and didn't know what to do with it, right? You
know, it's sort of like אין ארי דורס ונוהם מתוך קופה של
תבן *ein ari dores venohem mitoch kuppah shel teven*. A lion doesn't
trample and roar because he's eating a trough of a grain when
he has like a When he has a very subsistence diet, אלא
מתוך קופה של בשר. But when he's eating the flesh, then he
feels haughty and arrogant and he roars. So, when we have it
too good, that leads us
astray. אמר רבי יאשיה, Amar Rabbi Yoshiyah, עד ירבעם, Ad Yerovam, okay,
back to
Yerovam. עד ירבעם היו ישראל יונקים מעגל אחד, Ad Yerovam hayu Yisrael
yonkim me'egel echad, until Yerovam, they were nursing, suckling, right, because it's
from a calf, a cow, suckling from one calf. They were only
suffering the sin of one golden calf. מכאן ואילך, Mikan ve'eilach, from
that point on, משנים ושלשה עגלים, mishnayim ushloshah agalim, they were suffering
from two and a third ones. They were the two that he
did plus the third one of Moshe. So that was that, they
were, you know, suffering the sins of those three calves that of
the images, they're like suckling from the calf itself. אמר רבי יצחק,
Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, אין לך כל פורענות ופורענות שבאה לעולם שאין בה
אחד מעשרים וארבע בהכרע ליטרא של עגל הראשון. Ein lecha kol puranut
upuranut sheba'ah la'olam she'ein bah echad me'esrim ve'arba behachra litra shel egel
harishon. You have no bad things, this is also playing back to
that previous idea about bad times. Now it's not just the times,
but continuing to pay the sin. But, you know, what's the pasuk
says? וביום פקדי ופקדתי עליהם חטאתם. Uveyom pokdi ufochadeti aleihem chatatam. That
were always still slowly paying off the interest, the sin of that
original,
you know, of the original חטא העגל. cheit ha'egel. So he says
there's never anything bad that happens to the Jewish people, there isn't
a tiny little 1/24th of a liter meaning like, you know, when
you're sort of doing a balance of a scale, you add a
little bit extra on a side to make sure that the customer
is getting their, you know, is really getting the full amount. So
that tiny little bit, like that, you know, that one gram that
you add on the scales, every time that something bad is happening,
one gram of that is from the עגל הזהב. egel hazahav You
also wonder if the idea of the tipping of the scales also
indicates that maybe it's that one sin of the עגל הזהב that
led that was the thing that tipped the scales that we should
be punished right right right now. You know, it wasn't big, it's
only one gram, but sometimes it's the one gram that tips the
scales. Okay, שנאמר וביום פקדי ופקדתי עליהם חטאתם. Shene'emar uveyom pokdi ufochadeti
aleihem chatatam. אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chanina, לאחר עשרים וארבע דורות
נגבה פסוק זה. Le'achar esrim ve'arba dorot nigbah pasuk zeh. This pasuk
that God is going to punish us for the חטא העגל cheit
ha'egel was finally paid off after 24
generations. שנאמר ויקרא באזני קול גדול לאמר קרבו פקדות
העיר ואיש כלי משחתו בידו. Shene'emar vayikra be'oznai kol gadol leimor kirvu
pekudot ha'ir ve'ish kli mashchito beyado. The time of the visitation against
the city has arrived. This is about the destruction of the בית
המקדש. This is יחזקאל Yechezkel talking. Each person coming with their weapons
of destruction. And if you look at רש״י, Rashi, he does the
math and shows you that that was 24 generations when ירושלים Yerushalayim
was destroyed, 24 generations after חטא העגל. cheit ha'egel. Okay, so anyway,
so that's when it was, and again, it's the play on the
word of פקדתי pokadeti and פקדות pekudot or whatever, and the connection
of those words. That was when the חטא העגל cheit ha'egel was
paid. You do wonder is what he is also saying though that
maybe rather than thinking that we're constantly paying off חטא העגל, cheit
ha'egel, maybe this has a positive message like okay, we paid it
off once, 24 generations later, and, you know, and maybe it's not
constant, you know, as opposed to the previous position. Okay, אחר הדבר
הזה לא שב ירבעם מדרכו הרעה. Achar hadavar hazeh lo shav Yerovam
midarko hara'ah. After this thing Yerovam still did not return from his
evil ways. So מאי אחר, mai achar, what after what? What should
have made him return from his evil ways? So אמר רבי אבא,
Amar Rabbi Abba, אחר שתפסו הקדוש ברוך הוא לירבעם בבגדו. Achar shetefaso
HaKadosh Baruch Hu leYerovam bevigdo. God like is grabbing onto Yerovam by
his by his shirt, ואמר לו חזור בך, ve'amar lo chazor becha,
just do teshuva, ואני ובן ישי נטייל בגן עדן. ve'ani uven Yishai
netayel beGan Eden. You, me, and דוד המלך David HaMelech will be
alone in Gan Eden. You'll have you'll be right up there, just
do teshuva. אמר לו מי בראש, Amar lo mi berosh, who gets
to walk first? So בן ישי בראש. Ben Yishai berosh. Okay, David
is going to go walk first. אי הכי לא בעינא, Ei hachi
lo be'ina, then I don't want it. So that's obviously playing up
about גסות הרוח, gasut haruach, right? You know, he started off as
a good guy, but, you know, what is it? Power corrupts, right?
So and then at the end it was all just about his
honor and his power. רבי אבהו הוה רגיל דהוה קא דרש, Rabbi
Abbahu hava ragil dehava ka darash, so you know, I don't want
to give up my honor in this world if I'm not going
to be the top guy in the world
to come. Okay, רבי אבהו הוה רגיל דהוה קא דרש בשלושה מלכים.
Rabbi Abbahu hava ragil dehava ka darash bishloshah melachim. He used to,
you know, we've been spending I don't know two weeks already in
פרק חלק Perek Chelek here, he loved to talk about the פרק
חלק Perek Chelek and he loved specifically speaking about the three evil
kings and all the bad stuff they did and how they were
going to get punished. Okay, חלש, chalash, he got sick. Presumably, and
as we're going to see from the next story, presumably it means
like even with all the evil they did, they were also they
were also great people, and therefore, like, don't go overboard. So he
understood that the reason he got sick might have been because he
maybe went overboard talking about their evil deeds. So קיבל עליה דלא
דרש. Kibel aleih dela darash. So he said, okay, that's it, I
promise I won't talk about it anymore. Okay, and that maybe like
I went overboard. So כיון דאיתפח, Keivan de'itpach, so then got better.
So הדר קא דרש, Hadar ka darash, then he went back to
talking about it. So אמרי, Amri, so the students said to
him, לא קבילת עליך. lo kibeilta aleich. I don't understand. You accepted
upon yourself that you were not going to talk about this anymore.
אמר, amar, he
said, אינהו מהדרו בהו דאנא אהדר בי? inhu mihadru behu de'ana ahadar
bi? What? Did they stop doing their bad stuff that I should
stop doing what I'm doing? If they'd stopped doing their wickedness, I'd
stop talking about it.
Okay, of
course they did, but alright.
רב אשי Rav Ashi אוקי אשלשה מלכים. uki a-shlosha melachim. Now רב
אשי Rav Ashi was learning whatever he was learning, let's assume he's
learning חלק, Chelek, and he got right up to where we got
to yesterday, which was, you know, I don't know, the last thing
about הוגש שם באותיותיו hugash shem be-otiyotav and said, that's where he
stopped learning on one day and said tomorrow, he stopped right before
the שלשה מלכים shelosha melachim and he says, tomorrow we're going to
start talking about the שלשה מלכים. shelosha melachim. Okay, the three kings.
אוקי הש... uki hash... where were we? רב אשי Rav Ashi אוקי
אשלשה מלכים. uki a-shlosha melachim. אמר, למחר, lemachar, tomorrow, נפתח בחברין. niftach
be-chaverin. We'll talk about our colleagues. Why call the three kings your
colleagues? Again, what we saw the גמרא Gemara before about ירבעם, Yerovam
a tremendous תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, so with all that they were
evil, they were understood to be, you know, great men and great
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim etc. So he said our colleagues. Presumably, he
was considering that a sign of respect, even these evil kings, he's
calling, you know, colleagues of we the Rabbis. So what happened? So
אתא מנשה. ata Menashe. So מנשה, Menashe, who we haven't talked about
yet, but you know, probably he's the one king that we probably
think of as the most evil of the
three. He was mentioned in the משנה, Mishnah, or mentioned up in
our earlier discussion. דאיתחזי ליה בחלמיה. de-itchazi leh be-chelmeh. He appeared to
him in a dream. אמר, חברך וחברי דאבוך קרית לן? chavrecha ve-chavrei
de-avuch karisa lan? What? We're your pals now? You called us your
colleagues and your father's
colleagues? החוצפה. hachutzpah. מהיכא דבעית למישרא המוציא? me-heicha davis le-mishra ha-motzi?
After you make המוציא, hamotzi, where are you supposed to break the
bread from? Funny question to be asked, like that's like the biggest
הלכתית halakhic question. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar leh, לא ידענא. lo yadana.
I don't know. אמר ליה, amar leh, מהיכא דבעית למישרא המוציא לא
גמרת? me-heicha de-ba'at le-mishra ha-motzi lo gamirt?
You don't even know where you're supposed to break bread when you
make המוציא, hamotzi, meaning maybe it's like a very regular thing, you
make המוציא hamotzi every single day, and you don't even realize that
there's a proper place to be breaking the bread, וחברך קרית לן?
ve-chavrecha karisan? And you think we're your colleagues? אמר ליה, amar leh,
so before he got back to responding to the critique, he says
to him, first of all, אגמר לי, agmer li, first of all,
tell me where you break the bread, I want to know, ולמחר
דרשנא משמך בפרקא, ul-machar darishana mi-shmach be-pirka,
and tomorrow in the big public assembly I will say that King
מנשה Menashe teaches, you know, I'll teach this תורה Torah in your
name. So it's so funny the way the Rabbis make everybody into
תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar leh, מהיכא דקרים בישולא.
me-heicha de-karim bishula.
From where the cooking or the baking takes a crust. What does
that mean? A crust all around? So רש"י says maybe it means
you don't sort of go grab the inside part. You ever have
somebody who likes to just grab the inside
of a חלה? challah? No, you have to take it from the
outside, from the crust, or maybe from where it's more baked rather
than from where it's less baked. Again, it's so funny like why
does this really matter, but maybe that's the point, like if you
really knew תורה, Torah, you would really know that even these tiny
things matter in some level. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar leh, מאחר דחכימתו
כולי האי, me-achar de-chakimtu kulei hai, if you're so wise, so מאי
טעמא קפחיתו לעבודת כוכבים? mai ta'ama k-pachitu la-avodat kochavim? Why did you
go worship עבודת כוכבים? avodat kochavim? אמר ליה, amar leh, אי הות
התם, i havit hatam, if you were there, הות נקיטת בשיפולי גלימך,
havat nakitat be-shipulei glimach, this is such a famous story, you would
have picked up the skirts of your, like, you know, of your
cloak, ורהיטת בתראי, ve-rahitat basrai,
and you would be running after it. Like you don't know the
power of the seduction of עבודת כוכבים. avodat kochavim. It's easy for
you to judge. If you had been living then, you know, you
would be running after it. So למחר, lemachar, אמר להו לרבנן, amar
lehu le-rabbanan, so he took the מוסר. mussar. He appreciated like who
are we to judge based on our standards, right? So the next
day he said to the Rabbis, נפתח ברבוותא. niftach be-ravvata.
Let's start talking about the about the great our Rabbis, not our
colleagues. So you're going to still say they were רשעים, resha'im, but
you know, at the same time you're saying רשעים, resha'im, recognize that
they were, you know, give yourself some perspective and also recognize their
greatness.
Reflects back on all the stories you were just going through, right?
The two golden calves and everything?
Right? Yeah, like what you mean, like what motivated, right, I mean,
right, well, that's the גמרא Gemara telling us that through all this
that we're going to be talking about their evil, let's have a
little perspective. And it's also why while talking about their evil, it
was also talking about, you know, ירבעם Yerovam, was this great תלמיד
חכם. talmid chacham. Right? So it's this something really beautiful about that,
you know, about not, you know, not taking this like sort of,
you know, moral arrogance or, you know, whatever, this sense like a
moral superiority, right? I mean it's so common nowadays, you know, people
read all, you know, things from previous generations and how how could
they not have had the type of sensitivity we have today? You
know? So it's a real like appropriate humility and not, you know,
not putting yourself in those times, you know, you would probably, you
know, it's number one, and the appreciating the power of עבודת כוכבים
avodat kochavim and appreciating that people are complex, that even evil people
there can be greatness in them, you know, so. So, I think
there's a very powerful גמרא. Gemara Let's read a little bit more.
Now we move on from ירבעם Yerovam. to אחאב. Achav. Okay, אחאב
Achav once again with the worship of the בעל ba'al and his
wife איזבל. Izebel. אחאב, Achav, אח לשמים. ach lashamayim. אח לשמים ach
lashamayim sounds like a good thing, but actually we're going to use
the word אח ach like oy, you know, like woe to heaven.
Right. אב, av, אח-אב. Ach-Av. אב לעבודת כוכבים, av l'avodas kochavim, and
somebody who loves עבודה זרה. avodah zarah, אח לשמים ach lashamayim דכתיב:
dichsiv: אח לצרה יולד, ach l'tzara yulad, oy, a woe, somebody's just
born to anguish. אב לעבודת כוכבים av l'avodas kochavim דכתיב: dichsiv: כרחם
אב על בנים. k'rachem av al banim. He loved עבודה זרה. ויהי
הנקל לכתו בחטאת ירבעם בן נבט. vayehi hanekel lachto b'chatas Yerovam ben
Nevat. It was easy, like it was like trivial for him to
follow the sins of ירבעם. He did ירבעם ten times better, but
everything is in reference to ירבעם. אמר רבי יוחנן: amar Rabbi Yochanan:
קלות שעשה אחאב kalos she'asa Achav כחמורות שעשה ירבעם. k'chamuros she'asa Yerovam.
The trivial sins of אחאב Achav were as bad as the worst
sins of ירבעם. So he did ירבעם ten times worse. ומפני מה
תלה הכתוב בירבעם? u'mipnei mah tala haksav b'Yerovam? So then why does
it attribute it to ירבעם, not just him, other evil deeds of
other kings of Israel? שהוא היה תחילה לקלקלה. shehu hayah techilah l'kalkalah.
He was the one that started off the bad stuff. So Michael
before used the word paradigm.
I don't think I'd use the word paradigm. Paradigm sort of means
the model, but he was the one that sort of led everybody
astray, you know, and then everybody else was just being, continuing through
the whole, you know, flow of events and the whole culture and
everything that had been set in motion through ירבעם. Okay, גם מזבחותם
כגלים על תלמי שדי, gam mizbechosam kegalim al talmei sadai, even their,
you know, it was so terrible that they even put their altars
like mounds by the furrows of the field. אמר רבי יוחנן: amar
Rabbi Yochanan: אין לך כל תלם ותלם בארץ ישראל שלא העמיד עליו
אחאב עבודה זרה והשתחוה לו. ein lecha kol telem vetelem b'Eretz Yisrael
shelo he'emid alav Achav avodah zarah vehishtachavah lo. You don't have any
furrow in the land of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that he didn't
on every single furrow place an idol and bow down to it.
ומנלן דלא אתי לעולם הבא? u'menalan d'lo ati l'olam haba? Okay, so
how do you know he won't get עולם הבא? olam haba? You
know, he's really wicked, like, how do we know? Okay, דכתיב, dichsiv,
because the verse says: והכרתי
לאחאב משתין בקיר. v'hichrati l'Achav mashtin b'kir. I will wipe out for
אחאב Achav משתין בקיר mashtin b'kir literally means like men or whatever,
one who urinates against the wall. The גמרא Gemara reads it like
תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. ועצור ועזוב בישראל, v'atzur v'azuv b'Yisrael, and those
that are protected in Israel or held back. עצור בעולם הזה, atzur
ba'olam hazeh, whether you're in this world, ועזוב לעולם הבא v'azuv l'olam
haba or abandoned whatever the world to come, they'll all be wiped
out. And therefore אחאב, Achav, not just his descendants, but also reading
it as אחאב Achav himself won't get עולם הבא. olam haba. אמר
רבי יוחנן: amar Rabbi Yochanan: מפני מה זכה עמרי למלכות? mipnei mah
zachah Omri l'malchus? Why did עמרי, Omri, who was אחאב's Achav father,
I believe, why did he get מלכות? malchus? מפני שהוסיף כרך אחד
בארץ ישראל. mipnei shehosif kerach echad b'Eretz Yisrael. He was also evil.
Because he added a one city in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. שנאמר:
shene'emar: ויקן את ההר שמרון מאת שמר בככרים כסף. vayiken es hahar
Shomron me'es Shemer b'kicharayim kesef. He bought the mount שמרון, Shomron, I
mean that was Samaria,
from this person שמר, Shemer, that's why it was called שמרון, Shomron,
for these two talents of silver, בככרים כסף. b'kicharayim kesef.
ויבן את ההר vayiven es hahar and he built up the mountain,
ויקרא את שם העיר אשר בנה שם שמר, vayikra es shem ha'ir
asher banah shem Shemer, and he called it after the name of
שמר, Shemer, that's why it's called שמרון, Shomron, that's where you get
Samaria. על שם שמר אדני ההר, al shem Shemer adonei hahar, שמר
Shemer the owner of the mount, שמרון, Shomron, he called it שמרון.
Shomron. אמר רבי יוחנן: amar Rabbi Yochanan: מפני מה זכה אחאב למלכות?
mipnei mah zachah Achav l'malchus? Why did אחאב Achav merit מלכות malchus
if in the end he was so evil and he didn't even
start off as good? כ"ח שנים. kaf-ches shanim. It was a long
kingdom, right? Many of the kings were much shorter. מפני שכיבד את
התורה שניתנה בכ"ב אותיות. mipnei shekibed es hatorah shenitnah b'chaf-beis osiyos. He
honored the תורה torah that was given in twenty-two letters, twenty-two letters
of the Hebrew alphabet. How do we know he did this? שנאמר:
shene'emar: וישלח מלאכים אל אחאב מלך ישראל העירה ויאמר לו. vayishlach malachim
el Achav melech Yisrael hairah vayomer lo. So this בן הדד, Ben-Hadad,
right from this warring nation, sent messengers to אחאב Achav and he
said to him, כה אמר בן הדד, koh amar Ben-Hadad, this is
what בן הדד Ben-Hadad says, כספך וזהבך לי, kaspacha v'zehavcha li, your
silver and gold is all mine 'cause I can conquer you. ונשיך
ובניך הטובים לי הם, u'nashecha u'vanecha hatovim li hem, and your wives
and your beautiful children, they're all mine. כי אם כעת מחר, ki
im ka'es machar, unless you do the following thing, I'm going to
seize it all. אשלח את עבדי אליך, eshlach es avadai elecha, I
will send my servants to you, וחפשו את
ביתך ואת בתי עבדיך, vechipsu es beisecha v'es batei avadecha, and they'll
search out your house and the houses of your servants. והיה כל
מחמד עיניך ישימו בידם ולקחו, vehayah kol machmad eynecha yasimu beyadam velakachu,
and everything that's desirous in your house you give them and they'll
take it. So either give me all of your good stuff or
I'm just going to conquer you and take it all over tomorrow.
Okay, and that's what he did. And what was אחאב's Achav response?
ויאמר למלאכי בן הדד, vayomer lemalchei Ben-Hadad, so אחאב Achav said to
the messengers of הדד, Hadad, אמרו לאדני המלך, imru ladoni hamelech, tell
to my master king, he still knew that בן הדד Ben-Hadad was
still in power, you know, had greater power, but he says, כל
אשר שלחת אל עבדך בראשונה אעשה, kol asher shalachta el avdecha barishonah
e'eseh, all the initial things you asked for me I will do,
והדבר הזה לא אוכל לעשות, vehadavar hazeh lo uchal la'asos, but I
can't do this, I cannot give all my desirous things over in
your hand. So what was it that he wasn't giving? What was
holding him down? So מאי מחמד עיניך? mai machmad eynecha? What was
this desirous thing he didn't want to give up? לאו ספר תורה?
lav sefer torah? It's got to be the ספר תורה! sefer torah!
What is more desirous than the ספר תורה, sefer torah, more dear?
So you
see. Talk about like a little circular reasoning. So the גמרא says
ודילמא עבודת כוכבים, u-dilma avodat kochavim, I don't get it, he was
such an idolater, maybe he didn't want to give up his idols.
So no, לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka da'atcha. We see ויאמרו אליו
כל הזקנים וכל העם, vayomru elav kol ha-zkenim ve-chol ha-am,
all the elders of the people said to him אל תשמע ואל
תאבה, al tishma ve-al toveh,
don't listen, don't obey. So if all the people were supporting this
decision, it must have been that it was not and the זקנים,
zkenim, the elders, it couldn't have just been about not giving up
the idols. Okay, ודילמא סבי דבהתא, u-dilma savei de-vahata,
maybe they were just foolish elders, you know, maybe it doesn't mean
like wise, you know, sages, maybe it just means old people so
who are, you know, so ומי לא כתיב, u-mi lo ketiv, doesn't
it say וישר הדבר בעיני אבשלום ובעיני כל זקני ישראל va-yishar ha-davar
be-enei Avshalom u-ve-enei kol ziknei Yisrael and there ואמר רב יוסף ve-amar
Rav Yosef this rebellion of אבשלום, Avshalom, רב יוסף Rav Yosef says
סבי דבהתא, savei de-vahata, that was just foolish elders, it was not
the actual sages? So no, so the גמרא says לא, התם לא
כתיב וכל
העם. lo, hatam lo ketiv ve-chol ha-am.
No, by אבשלום Avshalom it doesn't say all the people, הכא כתיב
וכל העם, hacha ketiv ve-chol ha-am, all the people. So it's not
just that it says elders. Elders and all the people. You would
not have had unanimous consent, presumably somewhere in the people there would
have been somebody who did not agree to idolatry. So you would
not have had unanimous consent that it was about not giving over
the idols. The only thing you would have had unanimous consent about
was not giving over the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. So because this
מדרש midrash he protected the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, that was the
reason why he survived as a king for twenty-two years. די אפשר
דלא הוי בהו חד צדיק, di efshar de-lo havi behu chad tzadik,
it's impossible
that
there wasn't one person who was righteous. וכתיב והשארתי בישראל שבעת אלפים
כל הברכים אשר לא כרעו לבעל, u-ketiv ve-hish'arti ve-Yisrael shivat alafim kol
ha-birkayim asher lo char'u la-ba'al, I will keep in Israel all of
the
seven thousand all those knees that did not bend to the בעל.
Ba'al. וכל הפה אשר לא נשק לו ve-chol ha-peh asher lo nashak
lo and all the mouths that didn't kiss. So you see there
are always going to be even in idolatrous times some righteous people.
Okay, and we'll just see maybe I'll just read one more line.
אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman said רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, אחאב
שקול היה. Achav shakul haya. אחאב Achav was like, you know, a
בינוני. beinoni. He wasn't a רשע. rasha. He was a בינוני. beinoni.
He was exactly even, his sins and his merits. How do I
know it? שנאמר ויאמר השם מי יפתה את אחאב, shene'emar vayomer Hashem
mi yefateh et Achav, who will seduce אחאב Achav to sin, ויעל
ויפול ברמות גלעד, ve-ya'al ve-yipol be-ramot gil'ad, or to go to war
and he'll fall in רמות גלעד. Ramot Gil'ad. ויאמר זה בכה וזה
בכה vayomer zeh be-cho ve-zeh be-cho and all the different spirits in
front of God say this way and that way. So the fact
that he needed to be seduced for his downfall shows that he
wasn't yet a רשע, rasha, he was fifty-fifty. So the גמרא says
what are you talking about? So the גמרא says מתקיף לה רב
יוסף, matkif lah Rav Yosef, מה דכתיב ביה, mah de-chtiv beih, the
person of whom it says רק לא היה כאחאב, rak lo haya
che-Achav,
this, you know, king was not like אחאב Achav אשר התמכר, asher
hitmaker, he sold himself off לעשות הרע בעיני השם, la'asot ha-ra be-enei
Hashem, he dedicated himself to do evil in the eye of God.
אשר הסתה אותו איזבל
אשתו, asher hesatah oto Izavel ishto, because let's not forget איזבל Izavel
seduced him as well to do this. ותניא בכל יום הייתה שוקלת
שקלי זהב לעבודת כוכבים, ve-tanya be-chol yom hayta shokelet shiklei zahav la-avodat
kochavim, what did איזבל Izavel do because we mentioned before, what about
equal treatment? Okay, so now איזבל Izavel gets her due. Every day
she would weigh out like, you know, gold to give to
עבודה זרה. ואת אמרת שקול היה, ve-at amrat shakul haya, he was
like a בינוני, beinoni, what are you talking about? אלא אחאב, Ela
Achav, no, he was a total רשע. rasha. But there was one
thing that was protecting him. Okay, וותרן בממונו היה. vatran be-mamonoh haya.
We talked about איזבל Izavel was giving all this money to עבודה
זרה, אחאב Achav was very willing to give up his money. It's
very funny because אחאב Achav was the whole thing with the כרם,
kerem, right? Wasn't that אחאב Achav with the כרם נבות, kerem Navot,
right? Every so that was a particular thing he lusted after, he
desired, but general money he was generous with. Okay, ומתוך שנהנה תלמידי
חכמים מנכסיו, u-mitoch she-henah talmidei chachamim mi-nechasav,
back to it's all about תורה, Torah, because he supported תורה Torah
scholars one minute with his property, כיפרו לו מחצה. kiperu lo mechtzah.
So he was a total רשע rasha but God like waived half
of his sins. So I agree that like maybe in the weighing
it was, you know, half of his sins were taken off the
scale. But that doesn't mean he in his person was a בינוני.
beinoni. Okay, so yes, he still needed to be seduced to tip
the scales but it was because of this tremendous thing of צדקה.
tzedakah. So along the way where I'm talking about the complexity of
people like before and be talking about the power of certain מצוות,
mitzvot, you don't know מתן שכרן של מצוות matan scharan shel mitzvot
and צדקה tzedakah and so on and also of course, you know,
supporting תורה Torah and bringing the whole idea of תורה Torah scholarship
into the whole discussion. What did you want to say, מיכל? Michal?
Her money for עבודת כוכבים. avodat kochavim.
The money she was being שוקלת shokelet he gave. I'm not sure.
I mean I think there's a parallel but it's she was שוקלת
shokelet and he was וותרן בממונו. vatran be-mamonoh. I don't know. I
think it's a little bit of I don't know think it's the
same but I think it's a parallel. Okay. Okay, so we will
okay, so we'll pick up with this tomorrow.